Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 65: Miracles of Mary, circa 1720; 65; 2012-71; 154.0 Leaves Manuscript on parchment, mostly in gatherings of 10 leaves. The main body of the text is written in 2 columns of 15 lines, in black with the usual rubrics (opening lines of individual texts, the name of M
  - MIRACLE 29 [numbered as 30], circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 90v-92v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the cannibal of Qemer whose soul was saved by the Virgin Mary.
  - PAINTING 52, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 92v. (Unitid 65)
    A composite picture showing the cannibal dismembering his relatives; giving water to a leper; the farmers who set out to catch him. the two brief texts simply identify 'the cannibal' and 'the farmers'.
  - PAINTING 53, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 93r. (Unitid 65)
    A composite picture showing Christ commanding the devil to surrender the cannibal's soul; St. Michael weighing the cannibal's soul in the balance; the Virgin Mary with Christ's blessing retrieving the cannibal's soul.
  - MIRACLE 30 [numbered as 31], circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 93v-94v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the widow's son who was a thief, whom the Virgin saved at his mother's request.
  - PAINTING 54, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 94v. (Unitid 65)
    The thief steals from the Virgin's church.
  - PAINTING 55, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 95r. (Unitid 65)
    Top, the thief's mother prays before the Virgin's image; bottom, the thief is rescued by St. Michael from his bonds.
  - MIRACLE 31 [numbered as 32], circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 95v-96v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the woman who gave birth in a storm at sea with the Virgin's protection.
  - PAINTING 56, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 96v. (Unitid 65)
    [three-quarter page] The Virgin shields the woman and her child with her cloak, while the congregation look on from the shore. The text reads 'How she saved her'.
  - PAINTING 57, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 97r. (Unitid 65)
    The woman and her child amongst the congregation of her church. The text simply reads 'the faithful'.
  - MIRACLE 32 [numbered as 33], circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 97v-98v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the Virgin and the thirsty dog.
  - PAINTING 58, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 99r. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin gives water to the dog from her slipper, whilst below, her companions attempt to drive the dog away from the water jars.
  - blank, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 99v. (Unitid 65)
  - PAINTING 59, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 100r. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin and Child with the archangels and below, the prostrate figure of the donor or commissioner of the manuscript.
  - blank, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 100v. (Unitid 65)
  - blank except for two lines of pen trials, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 101r. (Unitid 65)
  - A hymn to the Virgin Mary, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 101v-104v. (Unitid 65)
    Beginning, "O Virgin, call to mind before the Keeper of Records who forgets nothing, call to mind, o Virgin, for my sake the birth through you of Him who was born in Bethlehem ...' Followed by a hymn of salutation [sälam] to the Virgin."
  - [different, larger hand], circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 105r-150v. (Unitid 65)
    a collection of hymns or songs to the Virgin Mary known as the Hymn or Canticle of the Flower [Mahlétä S'egé], beginning, "A flower appeared, shooting forth from the bone of him who greeted thee, the flower of Gabriel…".
  - blank leaf with a smaller [190 x 200mm] painted leaf sewn on, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 151r. (Unitid 65)
    containing a painting of an equestrian saint attacking a centaur. Two equestrian saints, Claudius [Gälawdéwos] and Victor [Fiqt'or] are shown in Ethiopian tradition spearing a centaur. There is no text to identify which saint is portrayed here. The painting is in the Second Gondarene style and can be dated to the 18th century.
  - blank, circa 1720; multiple folios; Located on folio 151v-154v. (Unitid 65)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 66: Book of Magico-Medical, Divinatory and Astrological Texts, late 19th century; 66; 145 Leaves Parchment manuscript in gatherings of various sizes, most frequently of 8. The thickness of the parchment varies considerably, and almost all leaves show signs of heavy wear, staining and rubbing. Single column text, varying number of lines (between 16 and 35), written in a mixture of Ge'ez and Amharic, variously in black with some rubrics, also in red, and in purple in a number of different hands. There are 32 charts and talismanic drawings (25 full-page, 7 part-page) in ink, and in addition there are 4 bifolia of coloured paintings inserted loosely into the manuscript. Bound in a plain parchment cover and preserved in a skin double carrying case with strap. 135 x 98 mm (Unitid 66)
  No specific owner's name is identifiable throughout, though several prayers contain the name of a certain Gäbrä Mika'él Täsämma (sometimes just given as Gäbrä Täsämma). In addition, one of the loose bifolia contains a picture of a certain Ato Amarä Zäbehéral (? end of the second name unclear). The various hands, all of which are of poor quality, together with the paintings on the inserts, which show some western pigments, are indicative of a late 19th cent. date.
  The text comprises a typîcal däbtära's manual of various magico-medical, divinatory and astrological texts together with sample talismanic drawings. Notable is the set of charts from the divinatory text, the Awdâ Nägäst, or Cycle of the Kings.
  - Various magico-medical prescriptions, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 1r-8r. (Unitid 66)
    In Amharic.
  - Prescriptions for undoing spells, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 8v-12r. (Unitid 66)
    In Amharic with some Ge'ez.
  - Various spells for combatting demons, the evil eye, etc., late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 12r-15v. (Unitid 66)
    incorporating magical names, in Ge'ez except for one [fols. 14v-15v] which is in part at least in Arabic, or what purports to be Arabic, written in Ethiopian script.
  - Prescription for curing typhoid or typhus, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.16r. (Unitid 66)
  - Talismanic drawing in the form of an eight-pointed star with a central face, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.16v. (Unitid 66)
  - Various magical prayers for binding and destroying demons, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 17r-22r. (Unitid 66)
    Placed within the text is a further talismanic drawing in the form of an eight-pointed star and a chart. The prayers also contain "magical" or talismanic letter-forms.
  - Talismanic drawing to accompany "the prayer of Moses", late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.22v. (Unitid 66)
  - Various talismanic drawings, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 23r-24v. (Unitid 66)
  - [blank], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.25r-v. (Unitid 66)
  - Talismanic drawing in the form of the cosmic serpent, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.26r. (Unitid 66)
  - Various magical prayers for the binding and destruction of demons, evil spirits, etc., late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 27r-35r. (Unitid 66)
    Within the text are placed 4 talismanic drawings and charts.
  - [blank], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.35v. (Unitid 66)
  - Prayer for "blocking" one's enemies, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 36r-37v. (Unitid 66)
  - Sequence (in various hands) of prayers with talismanic drawings for summoning demons, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 37v-39v. (Unitid 66)
  - Prayers for "harming those who harm [me]", late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 39v-43r. (Unitid 66)
  - Prayers, some unspecified, others for female ailments, incorporating lists of magical names [asmat], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 43v-51v. (Unitid 66)
  - Astrological computations [hasabä käwakebt], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 52r-56v. (Unitid 66)
  - Computations for predicting an individual's preferment or appointment to office [hasabä simät], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.57r-v. (Unitid 66)
  - Unidentified prayer, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 57v-58v. (Unitid 66)
  - Astrological text concerning "the will of 7 stars and 12 stars' [mäfqedä 7 käwakebt wäzä-12 käwakebt], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 58v-62v. (Unitid 66)
  - Collection of unidentified magical prayers, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 63r-64v. (Unitid 66)
  - "Calculation of hours [of daylight] and of darkness" [Sefrä sä'at wäs'elalot], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 65r-68r. (Unitid 66)
    For each of the months of the year, followed by a numerical chart given the hours of daylight and darkness for the month of Tahsas.
  - [blank], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.68v. (Unitid 66)
  - 16 charts of the Awdä Nägäst [The Cycle of the Kings], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 69r-76v. (Unitid 66)
    An Ethiopian text probably originally composed in the 15th cent., which by means of circular tables [awd] allows the diviner or fortune teller to find answers to specific questions posed by his clients. The 16 tables are each named after Ethiopian lakes or rivers.
  - Prayer addressed to Jesus Christ seeking divine blessing and protection from and power over devils and spirits, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 77r-78v. (Unitid 66)
  - Unidentified divinatory text, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.79r. (Unitid 66)
  - [blank except for a single line of text], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio f.79v. (Unitid 66)
  - Astrological text, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 80r-100r. (Unitid 66)
    In Amharic, with some Ge'ez.
  - A series (30 chapters or sections) of prescriptions for casting the fortunes of men and women, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 100v-118v. (Unitid 66)
    In Ge'ez, with some Amharic.
  - "The Book of Precise Knowledge" [Mäs'hafä Temhert T'eyyuq], late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 118v-123r. (Unitid 66)
  - A series of calculations [hasab] for divining various topics, such as success of a journey, birth of children, appointment to office, etc., late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio fols. 123r-145r. (Unitid 66)
    Mostly in Ge'ez but with occasional Amharic.
  - Loose Bifolium 1, late 19th century; 1 bifolium (Unitid 66)
    Unrelated to the text in which it is inserted.
    Front: St. George and the dragon.
    Interior: blank except for ball-pen scribbles.
    Back: Holy Trinity with the four evangelical zoa.
  - Loose Bifolium 2, late 19th century; 1 bifolium (Unitid 66)
    Front: Virgin and Child.
    Interior left: crowned figure of Christ in the iconography of the Ecce Homo.
    Interior right: Crucifixion.
    Back: blank except for a rough drawing of a face and a pen trial.
  - Loose Bifolium 3, late 19th century; 1 bifolium (Unitid 66)
    Front: plain cross.
    Interior left: male figure identified as Ato Amarä Behéral ( ?) with his rifle bearer; the text reads "how he put himself under the protection of Our lady Mary."
    Interior right: Ascension with the figures of Adam and Eve "risen from their sleep."
    Back: blank except for scribbles.
  - Loose Bifolium 4, late 19th century; 1 bifolium (Unitid 66)
    The style of the drawing of the fourth bifolia differs markedly from that of the other three, and is probably by a different artist.
    Front: faint drawing of a figure.
    Interior left: St. Michael.
    Interior right: scribbles.
    Back: blank except for faint scribbles.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 72: Unidentified Text, undated; 72; 20 folios 11 x 9.2 cm (Unitid 72)
  Gift of Bruce Willsie, Class of 1986 (AM 2015-45).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 73: Anaphora of Our Lady Mary of Cyriacus of Bhnsa, Office Prayers, circa 1800-1999; 73; 41 folios Parchment manuscript. 12 x 8 cm (Unitid 73)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 74: Missal, early 19th century; 74; 46 folios Parchment manuscript. 20.7 x 13.5 cm (Unitid 74)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 75: Asmat Prayer of the Disciples, 1900s; 75; 6 folios Parchment manuscript. 13 x 9 cm (Unitid 75)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 76: Office Prayers and Anaphora of Our Lord Jesus Christ, late 18th century; 76; 29 folios Parchment manuscript. 11.2 x 8.5 cm (Unitid 76)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 77: Homiliary in Honor of the Archangel Michael, 1800s; 77; 138 folios 20.5 x 18 cm (Unitid 77)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 78: Unidentified Text, undated; 78; 66 folios 24.5 x 18 cm (Unitid 78)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 79: Acts of Gabra Manfas, 1700s; 79; 48 folios Parchment manuscript. 18 x 16.5 cm (Unitid 79)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 80: Bible Manuscript Codex, Hymn book called Ziq, undated; 80; multiple folios; Vellum manuscript.; 19 x 15 cm (Unitid 80)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 81: Antiphonary for the Fast, 1800s; 81; 95 folios Parchment manuscript. 16 x 11 cm (Unitid 81)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 82: Psalter, early 18th century; 82; 153 folios Parchment manuscript. 18.2 x 15.5 cm (Unitid 82)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 83: Gadla Hawaryat Manuscript, undated; 83; multiple folios; 36.6 x 29.2 cm (Unitid 83)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 84: Magical Prayers to the Virgin Mary, 1800s; 84; multiple folios; 12.3 x 8.6 cm (Unitid 84)
  Gift of Bruce Willsie, Class of 1986 (AM 2015-41).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 85: Unidentified Text, 1800s; 85; multiple folios; 26 x 19 cm (Unitid 85)